Shouvik Sharma

400 E 33rd Street, Apt 515, Chicago, IL-60616 | Phone: 3124592008 | shouvik19@gmail.com | Linkedin | Github | Medium

SUMMARY

Over 3 years of comprehensive work experience in Data Science, Marketing Analytics and Business Intelligence in banking, retail, healthcare, and supply chain domains. Ability to solve complex business problems using ETL, Data Warehousing, Machine Learning and Exploratory Data Analysis by working independently, and designing analytical solutions.

EDUCATION

• MS in Data Science, Illinois Institute of Technology, GPA: 3.8

(Aug 2019 - May 2021)

Related Courses: Machine Learning, Big Data Technologies, Applied Statistics, Statistical Learning, Database Management, Data Preparation and Analysis, Introduction to Algorithm, Data Science Practicum.

• MS in Statistics, NMIMS University, GPA: 3.35

(Jul 2016 - Apr 2018)

Related Courses: Regression Analysis, Estimation, Testing of Hypothesis, Distribution Theory, Linear Algebra and Numerical Methods, Parametric Inference estimation, Probability Theory, Linear Models

• Certifications: Snowflake Pro Certification, SAS Certified Base Programmer for SAS 9, SAS Certified Predictive Modeler

SKILLS

- Programming: SQL, Python, R, SAS, Pyspark, HTML, C#, Excel VBA (Macros), Regex, NLP, Adobe Analytics.
- Big Data Ecosystem: Spark, Hadoop, MapReduce, Hive, Pig, Kafka, Flume.
- Cloud Technologies: AWS (S3, EC2, Lambda, Athena, RDS, Redshift, EMR), MATLAB.
- Tools: Tableau, Power BI, Powerpoint, RStudio, Jupyter, Ultipro, SPSS, Workday, MS Office, JIRA, Spotfire, MS Access, Looker.
- Libraries: Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Scikit-Learn, Keras, Nltk, Gensim, Scipy, Beautiful Soup, Domo.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Data Engineer at Daten Solutions Inc., Chicago:

(May 2020 - Present)

- Developed and automated data migration pipeline from SQL Server to Snowflake and performed dimensional modeling on the migrated data using version control in **GitHub** after breaking down strategic problems.
- Performed customer segmentation using k-mean clustering in AWS Sagemaker, further analyzed data to provide subject
 matter insights and recommended cluster-wise products using apriori algorithm which ultimately improved the top-line
 revenue by 4%.
- Created ad-hoc reports with quantitative and qualitative data to explain variation in success Metrics, to determine root cause.
- Developed statistical models like **ARIMA** using statsmodels package in **Jupyter Notebook**, the model achieved an overall accuracy of MAPE 5.96%.

Data Scientist – Practicum Student at Labelmaster, Chicago:

(May 2020 - Dec 2020)

- Predicted department-wise sales based on seasonal and external factors, further performed validation with A/B testing.
- Implemented Statistical methods like **SARIMAX, VAR** along with some hypothesis testing as well as Machine Learning (Deep Learning) Time-Series techniques to large sales data.
- Achieved an accuracy of MAPE 8% approx. on price forecasting using Deep Learning algorithms like LSTM and RNN, to showcase results further created dashboards using Tableau.

Business Analyst at Cartesian Consulting:

(Apr 2018- Jul 2019)

- Identified probable customer churn using Predictive Models in Python like **Logistic Regression**, **Decision Trees**, **Random Forest** and achieved a true positive rate (**recall**) of 84% for target customer retention and acquisition marketing campaigns.
- Predicted sales by time series forecasting using statistical concepts in Python using neural networks, ARIMAX and Prophet
 for inventory management by eliminating understocking and reducing overstocking by 56%.
- Identified the 'Most Valuable Customer' by leveraging the customer data and deploying Random Forest algorithm with True positive rate of 81%, this led to better customer targeting and improve yearly topline revenue by 13 %
- Generated visualizations using Tableau to analyze marketing metrics for making recommendations and supply chain analysis.

Business Analyst Intern at Nielsen India Inc.:

(May 2017 – July 2017)

- Worked with the Apache Spark Framework for customer analytics on NNTV, N-Power, Arianna and NLTV using Spark SQL
 queries on large scale datasets for developing flawless CRM (customer relationship management) campaigns.
- Built an RNN Neural Network model for Live positional trading using Keras package in python with an accuracy of 71 %.

Business Analyst at Tata Capital Financial Services Ltd.:

(Jul 2015- Jul 2016)

- Built KPIs and Regression models to predict customer life-time value, enhance propensity and scoring attributes.
- Accurately extracted insights and created dashboards using Tableau, Excel VBA (Macros), pivot tables and slicers.
- Formulated ad-hoc reports based on requirements gathered from various stake holders using **JIRA** to provide solutions.

PROJECTS

Stack Overflow Data Analysis Model (Language/Tools-Python, Jupyter Notebook, Spark, Hive, PySpark, Pig):

 Analyzed insights about questions posted on stack overflow by extracting large data sets using Google's big query data warehouse; discovered top spammers, expert users, and most valuable customers users by leveraging big data technologies such as Apache HiveQL, Apache Pig and Apache Sparks (git link)

Recommendation System using Yelp (Language/Tools- Python, Jupyter Notebook, NumPy, SciPy, pandas, scikit-learn):

- Built a personalized restaurant recommender web app using the Yelp dataset of restaurants by testing models like Pure Collaborative, Approximate Nearest Neighbor, K-NN, Naive Bayes and Hybrid Matrix
- Factorization on different hyperparameters which were tuned using the python library scikit optimizer (git link)

Image Mating using CelebAMask-HQ (Language/Tools- Google Colab, regression):

 Conducted Image Matting using the U-Net architecture of the Convoluted Neural Networks on the opensource Celeb-Mask dataset with an IOU Score of 92%

Inventory Optimization problem on Kaggle (Language/Tools- Google Colab, Tableau, R studio, Adobe Analytics):

• Forecasted the demand for LED televisions using different time-series forecasting methods with Holt-Winter's Smoothing method as the best method with MAPE of 20.760.

Electronic Vendor Database: (Language/Tools - MySQL, Java 8, HTML, CSS, Bootstrap):

• Constructed the ER Model and translated into Relational Schema implemented as SQL script.